<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>2024 CFA Level 1 Notes &#8211; Jamil Jahangir Sheikh</title>
	<atom:link href="/docs-tag/2024-cfa-level-1-notes/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 14:17:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blue-Business-Architecture-Design-Logo-Logos-150x150.png</url>
	<title>2024 CFA Level 1 Notes &#8211; Jamil Jahangir Sheikh</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Financial Reporting</title>
		<link>/docs/financial-reporting/</link>
					<comments>/docs/financial-reporting/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 16:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=321</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Financial reporting standards are critical for preparing accurate and informative financial reports. These standards ensure that the financial statements of a company provide the necessary information to investors, creditors, and other stakeholders, allowing them to make informed decisions. Understanding the underlying framework of financial reporting standards is essential for analysts to assess the valuation implications of financial statement elements and transactions. The Framework of Financial Reporting Standards Objective Financial reporting standards serve several key purposes: Standard-Setting Bodies and Regulatory Authorities Standard-Setting Bodies Standard-setting bodies are responsible for creating and maintaining financial reporting standards. They exist in virtually every national market and include: Regulatory Authorities Regulatory authorities recognize and enforce these standards. Examples include: These authorities have the legal power to enforce financial reporting requirements and exert control over entities participating in capital markets within their jurisdictions. While private sector standard-setting bodies can create accounting rules, these rules are only effective if regulators approve them. Regulatory authorities can also establish their own rules that override private sector decisions. The IASB Framework The IASB framework is designed to: Conceptual Framework Objectives Key Users of Financial Statements User Needs Users require information about a company&#8217;s: Information that helps users assess future net cash inflows includes: Qualitative Characteristics of Financial Reports Relevance Relevant information affects users&#8217; decisions, has predictive and confirmatory value, and must be material. Faithful Representation Information must be complete, neutral, and free from error. Comparability Financial reports should allow users to identify similarities and differences between items consistently over time and across entities. This characteristic ensures that users can compare financial information across different periods and entities to make informed decisions. Verifiability Verifiability ensures that different independent observers would agree that the information faithfully represents economic phenomena. This characteristic enhances the reliability of financial reports by providing assurance that reported information is accurate and unbiased. Timeliness Timeliness means that information is available to decision-makers before it loses its ability to influence decisions. Providing timely information ensures that users can make well-informed decisions based on the most current data. Understandability Clear and concise presentation enhances comprehension, making it accessible to users with reasonable knowledge of business and economics. Information should be presented in a way that is easy to understand without sacrificing complexity and detail. Major Financial Statements Overview Equity or Credit Analysis Financial Reports Types of Financial Statements Important Elements of Financial Statements Balance Sheet/ Financial Position By using the balance sheet and analyzing financial statements, analysts can address several key questions: Has the company&#8217;s liquidity improved? Is the company solvent? What is the company&#8217;s financial position relative to industry peers? Income Statement An income statement can also include other income and expenses, such as gains or losses from the sale of assets or investments. Analysts use this statement to assess profitability and understand how revenue is generated and expenses are managed. Consolidated Income Statement: Minority Interests (Non-controlling Interests): Allocation of Net Income: Earnings Per Share (EPS): Other Comprehensive Income (OCI): Statement of Changes in Equity and Cash Flow Statement: Cash Flow Statement:]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Financial reporting standards are critical for preparing accurate and informative financial reports. These standards ensure that the financial statements of a company provide the necessary information to investors, creditors, and other stakeholders, allowing them to make informed decisions. Understanding the underlying framework of financial reporting standards is essential for analysts to assess the valuation implications of financial statement elements and transactions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Framework of Financial Reporting Standards</h2>



<p><strong>Objective</strong></p>



<p>Financial reporting standards serve several key purposes:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Provide principles for preparing financial reports</strong>: These principles determine the types and amounts of information that must be included in financial statements. This allows users, such as investors and creditors, to make well-informed decisions based on accurate and relevant data.</li>



<li><strong>Facilitate an understanding of the financial reporting framework</strong>: This broader framework helps analysts assess the valuation implications of financial statement elements and transactions. It goes beyond specific accounting rules and includes transactions that may represent new developments not specifically addressed by the standards.</li>



<li><strong>Ensure consistency in judgment</strong>: Uncertainty in various aspects of transactions often requires accruals and estimates, necessitating judgment from preparers. Standards aim to limit the range of acceptable answers, increasing consistency across financial reports.</li>



<li><strong>Develop comparable frameworks</strong>: The IASB and the US-based FASB have developed similar financial reporting frameworks that specify the overall objective and qualities of information to be provided.</li>



<li><strong>Enhance valuation processes</strong>: Although not solely focused on asset valuation, financial reports provide crucial inputs for valuing a company or its issued securities. Understanding the financial reporting framework helps analysts evaluate reported information and use it appropriately when assessing a company’s financial performance.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Standard-Setting Bodies and Regulatory Authorities</h2>



<p><strong>Standard-Setting Bodies</strong></p>



<p>Standard-setting bodies are responsible for creating and maintaining financial reporting standards. They exist in virtually every national market and include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>International Accounting Standards Board (IASB)</strong></li>



<li><strong>Financial Accounting Standards Board (FASB)</strong></li>



<li><strong>Private Sector Organizations</strong></li>



<li><strong>Self-Regulated Bodies</strong></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Regulatory Authorities</strong></p>



<p>Regulatory authorities recognize and enforce these standards. Examples include:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Accounting and Corporate Regulatory Authority (ACRA) in Singapore</strong></li>



<li><strong>Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) in the United States</strong></li>



<li><strong>Securities and Exchange Commission of Brazil</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>These authorities have the legal power to enforce financial reporting requirements and exert control over entities participating in capital markets within their jurisdictions. While private sector standard-setting bodies can create accounting rules, these rules are only effective if regulators approve them. Regulatory authorities can also establish their own rules that override private sector decisions.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The IASB Framework</h2>



<p>The IASB framework is designed to:</p>



<ul>
<li>Develop and promote the use and adoption of a single set of high-quality financial standards.</li>



<li>Ensure these standards result in transparent, comparable, and decision-useful information while considering the needs of various entities in diverse economic settings.</li>



<li>Promote the convergence of national accounting standards and IFRS.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Conceptual Framework Objectives</strong></p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Assist standard setters</strong>: Helps in developing and reviewing standards.</li>



<li><strong>Aid preparers</strong>: Guides in applying standards and addressing issues not specifically covered by existing standards.</li>



<li><strong>Assist auditors</strong>: Helps in forming opinions on financial statements.</li>



<li><strong>Assist users</strong>: Aids in interpreting financial statement information.</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>Key Users of Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Investors</strong></li>



<li><strong>Lenders</strong></li>



<li><strong>Creditors</strong></li>
</ul>



<p><strong>User Needs</strong></p>



<p>Users require information about a company&#8217;s:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Position</strong>: Resources and financial obligations.</li>



<li><strong>Financial Performance</strong>: How and why the company&#8217;s financial position changed over time.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Position</strong>: How the company obtained and used cash.</li>
</ul>



<p>Information that helps users assess future net cash inflows includes:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Economic Resources (Assets)</strong>: What the entity owns that has value and can generate future benefits.</li>



<li><strong>Claims Against the Entity (Liabilities and Equity)</strong>: Details about what the entity owes and the ownership interests in the entity.</li>



<li><strong>Management and Governing Board Effectiveness</strong>: Insights into how well the company&#8217;s management and board have utilized resources to create value.</li>
</ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Qualitative Characteristics of Financial Reports</h2>



<p><strong>Relevance</strong></p>



<p>Relevant information affects users&#8217; decisions, has predictive and confirmatory value, and must be material.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Affects Users&#8217; Decisions</strong>: Information should influence economic decisions.</li>



<li><strong>Predictive Value</strong>: Helps forecast future outcomes.</li>



<li><strong>Confirmatory Value</strong>: Assists in evaluating past predictions or performance.</li>



<li><strong>Materiality</strong>: Information is material if its omission or misstatement could influence users&#8217; decisions. Materiality depends on the nature and magnitude of the information&#8217;s impact.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Faithful Representation</strong></p>



<p>Information must be complete, neutral, and free from error.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Complete</strong>: All necessary information is provided.</li>



<li><strong>Neutral</strong>: Presented without bias.</li>



<li><strong>Free from Error</strong>: There are no errors of commission (incorrect information) or omission (important information left out). The process used to gather and report the information was appropriate and followed correctly without errors.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Comparability</strong></p>



<p>Financial reports should allow users to identify similarities and differences between items consistently over time and across entities. This characteristic ensures that users can compare financial information across different periods and entities to make informed decisions.</p>



<p><strong>Verifiability</strong></p>



<p>Verifiability ensures that different independent observers would agree that the information faithfully represents economic phenomena. This characteristic enhances the reliability of financial reports by providing assurance that reported information is accurate and unbiased.</p>



<p><strong>Timeliness</strong></p>



<p>Timeliness means that information is available to decision-makers before it loses its ability to influence decisions. Providing timely information ensures that users can make well-informed decisions based on the most current data.</p>



<p><strong>Understandability</strong></p>



<p>Clear and concise presentation enhances comprehension, making it accessible to users with reasonable knowledge of business and economics. Information should be presented in a way that is easy to understand without sacrificing complexity and detail.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Major Financial Statements Overview</strong></h3>



<p><strong>Equity or Credit Analysis</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Analysis integrates data on the economy, industry, and company, alongside information from comparable peers.</li>



<li>External sources include economic statistics, industry reports, trade publications, and competitor databases.</li>



<li>Core company information is sourced from its website, financial reports, press releases, investor calls, and webcasts.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Financial Reports</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Issued at regular intervals.</li>



<li>Comprise financial statements and supplementary disclosures.</li>



<li>Reports are consolidated, incorporating subsidiary balances controlled by the parent company.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Types of Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Balance Sheet (BS):</strong> Provides a snapshot of financial condition at a specific date.</li>



<li><strong>Statement of Comprehensive Income:</strong> Can be presented as a single statement or as two separate statements (income statement and statement of comprehensive income), beginning with profit or loss.</li>



<li><strong>Changes in Equity:</strong> Details alterations in financial position over time.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Flow Statement (CF):</strong> Tracks cash movements during the reporting period.</li>



<li><strong>Notes/Footnotes:</strong> Provide additional context and details to financial statements.</li>



<li><strong>Additional Information:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chairman&#8217;s Letter:</strong> Overview of company performance, strategy, and key achievements/challenges.</li>



<li><strong>Management Discussion and Analysis (MD&amp;A):</strong> Insights into financial performance, operational results, key business drivers, and future prospects.</li>



<li><strong>External Auditor&#8217;s Report:</strong> Assures accuracy and fairness of financial statements and reviews internal controls.</li>



<li><strong>Governance Report:</strong> Details board composition, roles, governance practices, and regulatory compliance.</li>



<li><strong>Corporate Responsibility Report:</strong> Covers initiatives and performance in areas like environmental sustainability, social responsibility, and stakeholder engagement.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Important Elements of Financial Statements</h2>



<p><strong>Balance Sheet</strong>/ Financial Position</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Assets</strong>: Owns, a right, controlled, have economic value, produce economic benefit. Ex. current (cash, inventory, receivables) and non-current (property, plant, equipment) assets.</li>



<li><strong>Liabilities</strong>: Owes, the present obligation to transfer economic resources as a result of a past event. Ex. current (payables, short-term debt) and non-current (long-term debt, bonds payable).</li>



<li><strong>Equity</strong>: Residual interest = (Assets &#8211; Liabilities)</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>IFRS mandates that balance sheets distinguish between current and non-current assets and liabilities.</li>



<li>There is no required order or format for how these items must be presented.</li>



<li>Presentation order often follows traditional practices.</li>



<li>Some companies arrange their balance sheets with non-current assets before current assets, owners&#8217; equity before liabilities, and non-current liabilities before current liabilities, following a sequence from least liquid to most liquid.</li>



<li>In contrast, companies in the U.S., Australia, and Canada typically list assets and liabilities from most liquid to least liquid, starting with &#8220;Cash&#8221; or &#8220;Cash and Equivalents,&#8221; and placing equity after liabilities.</li>
</ul>



<p>By using the balance sheet and analyzing financial statements, analysts can address several key questions:</p>



<p><strong>Has the company&#8217;s liquidity improved?</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Analysts assess the company&#8217;s ability to meet short-term financial obligations by examining current assets like cash, receivables, and inventory relative to current liabilities. Improved liquidity is indicated by a higher ratio of current assets to current liabilities, suggesting a stronger capacity to cover short-term debts.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Is the company solvent?</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Solvency analysis involves evaluating whether the company has sufficient assets (both current and non-current) to cover its liabilities. Analysts determine solvency by comparing total assets to total liabilities. If assets exceed liabilities, the company is considered solvent. Positive shareholder equity further supports solvency by confirming that assets surpass liabilities.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>What is the company&#8217;s financial position relative to industry peers?</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Comparative analysis involves benchmarking the company&#8217;s financial ratios (such as liquidity ratios, solvency ratios, and profitability ratios) against industry averages or competitors. This comparison helps gauge the company&#8217;s performance and financial health relative to its peers. Higher ratios indicate better financial health compared to industry norms, while lower ratios may signal potential weaknesses.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Income Statement</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>The income statement, also known as the profit and loss statement, shows a company&#8217;s financial performance over a specific period. It details:</li>



<li><strong>Revenue</strong>: The income earned from the sale of goods or services.</li>



<li><strong>Expenses</strong>: The costs incurred to generate revenue, including cost of goods sold, operating expenses, and income tax expenses. <strong>Decrease</strong>s in<strong> assets</strong> or<strong> increases</strong> in<strong> liabilities</strong>, excluding distributions to equity holders</li>



<li><strong>Net Income</strong>: The profit remaining after all expenses have been deducted from revenue. This is often referred to as net profit or net earnings. <strong>Increases</strong> in <strong>assets</strong> or <strong>decreases</strong> in <strong>liabilities</strong>, excluding contributions from equity holders</li>
</ul>



<p>An income statement can also include other income and expenses, such as gains or losses from the sale of assets or investments. Analysts use this statement to assess profitability and understand how revenue is generated and expenses are managed.</p>



<p><strong>Consolidated Income Statement:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Merges the financial results of a parent company with those of its subsidiaries into a single report.</li>



<li>Each line item reflects the total from the equivalent line item on the subsidiary&#8217;s income statement.</li>



<li>Internal transactions between the parent and subsidiary are omitted to avoid double counting.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Minority Interests (Non-controlling Interests):</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>If the parent company does not fully own a subsidiary, the remaining shares are held by minority interests or non-controlling interests.</li>



<li>These shareholders are entitled to a portion of the subsidiary&#8217;s profits based on their ownership percentage.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Allocation of Net Income:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>The parent company must separate net income attributable to its own shareholders from that attributable to minority interests.</li>



<li>Income for minority interests is subtracted from the consolidated net income at the bottom of the income statement.</li>



<li>This distinction ensures clarity in showing the profit distribution between the parent company&#8217;s shareholders and the minority shareholders.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Earnings Per Share (EPS):</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Both basic and diluted EPS are shown on the income statement.</li>



<li>EPS measures net income attributable to shareholders divided by the number of shares outstanding during the period.</li>



<li>Basic EPS is determined using the weighted-average number of common shares actually outstanding during the period and the corresponding profit or loss.</li>



<li>Diluted EPS considers the potential increase in shares if dilutive securities (like stock options or convertible bonds) are exercised or converted, adjusting the profit or loss accordingly.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Other Comprehensive Income (OCI):</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Comprehensive income encompasses all changes affecting owners&#8217; equity, excluding transactions directly involving shareholders.</li>



<li>It includes gains or losses from sources other than regular business operations, such as changes in investment market values or foreign currency translations.</li>



<li>These changes are divided into two categories:
<ul>
<li>Items impacting net income, which reflects profits or losses from core business operations.</li>



<li>Items classified under OCI, which include gains or losses impacting equity but not included in net income, like unrealized gains/losses on investments and certain pension adjustments.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Reporting comprehensive income typically begins with net income from the income statement followed by OCI components, ensuring transparent disclosure of all financial impacts on owners&#8217; equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Statement of Changes in Equity and Cash Flow Statement:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>The statement of changes in equity tracks changes in owners’ investment in the business over time.</li>



<li>It details for each equity component: beginning balance, increases, decreases, and ending balance.</li>



<li>Components include:
<ul>
<li>Paid-in Capital: Increases with new equity issuances and decreases with stock repurchases.</li>



<li>Retained Earnings: Cumulative profits retained in the company; increases with income (from income statement and OCI) and decreases with dividends.</li>



<li>Non-controlling interests and reserves representing accumulated OCI items may be separately reported or included in retained earnings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Cash Flow Statement:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Essential for assessing a company’s long-term viability.</li>



<li>Reveals sources and uses of cash, aiding evaluation of liquidity, solvency, and financial flexibility.</li>



<li>Contrasts with net income, which can be influenced by accrual accounting and management policy.</li>



<li>Direct method reports major cash receipts and payments (e.g., from customers, suppliers); however, indirect method aligns cash flows with income statement items, reflecting different perspectives but is more commonly used.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/financial-reporting/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Essential Financial Statement Analysis Terminology</title>
		<link>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/</link>
					<comments>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 16:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=319</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Learn about the key terminology that underpins the interpretation of balance sheets, income statements, and cash flow statements]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Financial statement analysis is a critical skill for investors, analysts, and stakeholders seeking to understand the financial health and performance of a company. To effectively analyze financial statements, one must be familiar with key terminology that underpins the interpretation of balance sheets, income statements, and cash flow statements. Below are some frequent terms and definitions to know:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Accruals</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Accruals refer to revenues and expenses that have been recognized on the income statement before cash is exchanged. This concept is fundamental to accrual accounting, which matches revenues to the expenses incurred in generating them, rather than when payment is received or made.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Estimates</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Estimates involve the use of judgments and assumptions to determine values that are not directly observable. Examples include estimating the useful life of an asset for depreciation purposes or estimating the provision for bad debts.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Judgment</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Judgment refers to the exercise of discretion or discernment in making decisions, particularly in the context of financial reporting. It involves the application of professional skepticism and consideration of relevant facts and circumstances.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Management Policy Decisions</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Management policy decisions encompass the strategic choices made by a company&#8217;s management that impact financial reporting and operational outcomes. These decisions can include revenue recognition policies, inventory valuation methods, and capital expenditure policies.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Consistency</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Consistency in financial reporting refers to the application of accounting policies and methods consistently from one period to another. This allows for comparability of financial statements over time and enhances the reliability of financial analysis.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Carrying Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Carrying value, also known as book value, refers to the value at which an asset or liability is recognized on the balance sheet. It is usually the original cost less accumulated depreciation or amortization, impairment losses, or depletion.</li>



<li><strong>Historical Cost &#8211; Acc. Depreciation</strong></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recoverable Amount</strong></h4>



<p>Higher of the (fair value &#8211; costs to sell) &amp; (value in use)</p>



<p>Where,</p>



<ul>
<li>Fair value  &#8211; Amount obtainable in an arm&#8217;s length transaction</li>



<li>Value in use &#8211; Present value of future cash flows</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Impairment</strong></h4>



<p>This occurs when the<strong> carrying value </strong>of an asset <strong>exceed</strong>s its <strong>recoverable amount.</strong> The impairment loss is calculated as the difference between the carrying amount and the recoverable amount.</p>



<p>Impairment Loss = Carrying Value &#8211; Recoverable Amount</p>



<p><strong>Impact on Financial Statements:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Income Statement:</strong> Recognizes impairment loss as an <strong>expense</strong>, reducing net income for the period.</li>



<li><strong>Balance Sheet:</strong> <strong>Adjusts </strong>the carrying amount of the impaired asset to its recoverable amount, reducing <strong>total assets</strong>.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Flow Statement:</strong> This does not directly impact cash flows from operating activities but may affect <strong>investing activities</strong> if the <strong>impairment loss relates to non-current assets.</strong></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Fair Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Fair value is the estimated price at which an asset or liability could be exchanged in an orderly transaction between knowledgeable and willing parties. Fair value measurements are used when assets and liabilities are reported at fair value on the balance sheet.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Realizable (Settlement) Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Realizable value, also known as settlement value, is the amount that would be received from selling an asset or settling a liability in an orderly transaction. It is crucial in assessing the liquidity and solvency of a company.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Accrual Accounting</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Accrual accounting is an accounting method that recognizes revenues and expenses when they are incurred, regardless of when cash transactions occur. It aims to provide a more accurate representation of a company&#8217;s financial position and performance.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Going Concern</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Going concern assumption assumes that a company will continue to operate in the foreseeable future. This assumption is fundamental in preparing financial statements under generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP).</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recognition of Elements</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Recognition of elements involves including an item in the balance sheet or income statement if it meets the definition of an element (asset, liability, equity, income, or expense) and satisfies specific recognition criteria related to relevance and faithful representation.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Book Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Book value refers to the total amount of owner&#8217;s equity, also known as shareholders&#8217; equity, in a company. It represents the net assets of the company after deducting liabilities from assets.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Minority Interests (Non-controlling Interests)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Minority interests, or non-controlling interests, refer to the ownership stake in a subsidiary that is not owned by the parent company. These shareholders have a claim on the subsidiary&#8217;s profits and assets proportionate to their ownership percentage.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Allowance for Doubtful Accounts: (B/S item)</strong></h4>



<p>Accounts for expected losses from uncollectible receivables. Increases in this allowance correspondingly raise Bad debt expense is an accounting provision that represents the amount of expected losses from customers who are unable to pay their debts. It is recorded in the income statement as an expense.. When a debt is written off, only the allowance and accounts receivable are reduced, leaving bad debt expense unchanged.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Percentage of Uncollectable Receivable</strong></h4>



<p>% Uncollectable = Allowance for doubtful accounts/ Gross accounts receivable</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Bad Debt Expense (I/S Item)</strong></h4>



<p>When expected losses is added to allowance for doubtful accounts, the Bad debt expense is also increased by the same amount, it is an accounting provision that represents the amount of expected losses from customers who are unable to pay their debts. It is recorded in the income statement as an expense.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Concentration of Credit Risks</h4>



<p>Reported in notes &#8211; List of all customers that owe money in terms of % of AR they represent</p>



<p>Every time we add to Allowance for doubtful account, we add the same amount in Bad Debt Expense. So, in case of a write off, we only reduce the balance in the Allowance for doubtful account and in Accounts Receivable while Bad Dabt Expense remain untouched.</p>



<p>For Analysts, if you see a % change in the Allowance for doubtful accounts, find out why &#8211; Is there a change in Risk Management (more insurance), credit quality (better economy), or management change in estimates (could be to manipulate reported earnings (Overestimate Collectability, Underestimate Bad Debt Expense or Vice Versa).</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Revenue</h4>



<p>Amount charged for delivery of goods in the ordinary activities of a business. A.K.A. Sales / Turnover / Top line</p>



<p>Usually reported as Net Revenue ( After adjustments for Cash or volume discounts or other reductions in the revenue). Footnotes may mention of the items. </p>



<p>For comparative analysis,&nbsp; analyst may need to reference information disclosed elsewhere in companies’ annual reports</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Expenses</h4>



<p> Outflows &#8211; Depletion of assets &#8211; insurance of liabilities</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Net Income</h4>



<p><strong>Definition:</strong> Net income, also referred to as net earnings, profit or loss, profit of the year, or bottom line, is the total profit of a company after all expenses, taxes, and costs have been deducted from total revenue. It represents the company&#8217;s financial performance over a specific period.</p>



<p><strong>Components:</strong> Net income includes all gains and losses, even those not arising from ordinary business activities. For example, if a company sells surplus land that is not needed for operations, the transaction is reported as a gain or loss, calculated as the difference between the carrying value (the asset&#8217;s book value) and the selling price.</p>



<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> Details of such non-ordinary gains or losses are typically found in the financial statement disclosures, providing context and specifics about the nature and amount of these transactions.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Consolidation</h4>



<p><strong>Definition:</strong> Consolidation is the accounting process where a parent company combines the financial statements of its subsidiaries into one comprehensive set of financial statements. This occurs when the parent company has control over the subsidiary, typically evidenced by owning more than 50% of the subsidiary&#8217;s voting shares.</p>



<p><strong>Inclusion of Revenues and Expenses:</strong> When consolidating, the parent company includes all revenues and expenses of its subsidiaries in its consolidated financial statements, regardless of whether it owns less than 100% of the subsidiary. This ensures that the financial statements reflect the total economic activity and financial position of the combined entity.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Noncontrolling Interest</strong></h5>



<p>Noncontrolling interest, also known as minority interest, represents the portion of the subsidiary&#8217;s income that is attributable to shareholders other than the parent company. This is the part of the subsidiary&#8217;s net income and equity that &#8220;belongs&#8221; to the minority shareholders and is reported separately in the consolidated financial statements.</p>



<p>We use the whole of a subsidiary in the consolidated statement. To balance the Asset and liability with Equity, we add the noncontrolling interests in the equity (Portion of subsidiary not that is not owned by the parent).</p>



<p><strong>Note For Analysts:</strong><br><strong>No Minority Interest:</strong> If there is <strong>goodwill</strong> on the balance sheet (Asset) but no minority interest in the equity, it means the parent company has fully acquired the subsidiary, owning 100% of its shares. Therefore, there are no minority shareholders.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Deferred Tax Assets</h4>



<p>Arise from temporary differences where the tax paid exceeds the tax expense reported on the income statement. It happens when you prepaid more than what is shown in the Income Statement due to Tax reporting and financial reporting differences. It may be amortized over several periods for accounting purposes</p>



<p>Represent future tax benefits due to overpayments or tax credits carried forward.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Accured Liability</h4>



<p>Accrued liabilities are expenses that have been reported on a company’s income statement but have not yet been paid.</p>



<p><strong>Example with Salary:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Suppose a company&#8217;s employees are paid on a bi-weekly basis, with the next payday falling after the end of the current accounting period.</li>



<li>At the end of the accounting period (e.g., December 31st), the company has accrued salaries owed to employees for the last few days of December.</li>



<li>Although the company hasn&#8217;t yet paid these salaries, it records them as an accrued liability on the balance sheet to reflect the amount owed.</li>



<li>This accrued liability ensures that the company&#8217;s financial statements accurately reflect its obligations and expenses incurred during the reporting period, even if cash payment occurs later.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Shares</h2>



<p>Shares (or stocks) typically refer to ownership units in a corporation. These shares can be categorized into different types based on the rights and privileges they confer to their holders. Here are the common types of shares:</p>



<p><li><strong>Capital Contributed by Owners:</strong><ul><li>The funds invested by shareholders through the purchase of shares, forming part of shareholders&#8217; equity.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Authorized Shares:</strong><ul><li>The maximum number of shares the company can issue, providing future financing flexibility.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Issued Shares:</strong><ul><li>The shares sold to investors, representing distributed ownership and capital raised.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Outstanding Shares:</strong><ul><li>The issued shares currently held by investors, used for financial calculations, excluding repurchased (treasury) shares.</li></ul></li></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Common Shares (Ordinary Shares)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Common shares are the most basic form of ownership in a corporation. Holders of common shares have voting rights in corporate decisions, such as the election of directors and major business decisions. They also have the potential to receive dividends, although these are not guaranteed and can fluctuate based on the company&#8217;s profitability and management decisions. In the event of liquidation, common shareholders are entitled to a portion of the company&#8217;s assets after creditors, bondholders, and preferred shareholders are paid.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preferred Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Preferred shares are a class of ownership that typically does not carry voting rights but has a priority claim on dividends and assets over common shares. Preferred shareholders receive fixed dividends, which are often specified as a percentage of the share&#8217;s par value or as a fixed dollar amount. These dividends must be paid before any dividends can be distributed to common shareholders. In the event of liquidation, preferred shareholders have a priority claim on the company&#8217;s assets over common shareholders but are subordinate to creditors.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Redeemable Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Redeemable shares are shares that the issuer can buy back from shareholders at a predetermined price and time. These shares provide flexibility to the issuing company by allowing them to manage their capital structure effectively. The terms of redemption are typically outlined in the company&#8217;s articles of incorporation or shareholder agreements.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treasury Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Treasury shares are shares that have been repurchased by the issuing company and are held in its treasury. These are shares that have been repurchased by the company but not canceled and can be reissued or retired depending on the company&#8217;s capital needs and strategic objectives.</li>



<li>Non-Voting / No Dividends.</li>



<li>Share repurchases reduce the company’s cash (an asset). Shareholders’ equity is reduced because there are fewer shares outstanding and treasury stock is an offset to owners’ equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Share Repurchases Impact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>When a company repurchases its own shares from the market, it uses cash to buy back these shares.</li>



<li>This reduces the company&#8217;s cash balance, which is categorized as an asset on the balance sheet.</li>



<li>Additionally, the number of shares outstanding decreases because the company holds these repurchased shares as treasury stock.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Effect on Shareholders&#8217; Equity:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Shareholders&#8217; equity decreases because there are fewer outstanding shares.</li>



<li>Treasury stock is subtracted from the total equity (owners&#8217; equity) on the balance sheet, acting as a contra-equity account.</li>



<li>The reduction in shareholders&#8217; equity reflects the decrease in the company&#8217;s ownership interest held by shareholders due to the share repurchase.</li>
</ul>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reasons for Repurchasing Treasury Shares:</strong></h5>



<ul>
<li><strong>Shares Undervalued:</strong>
<ul>
<li>When a company believes its shares are undervalued in the market, it may repurchase its shares to signal confidence in the company&#8217;s prospects and potentially boost the share price. This can enhance shareholder value as the market perceives the buyback as a positive signal about the company&#8217;s future.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>To Fulfill Options:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Companies often repurchase shares to have a reserve of stock available to fulfill employee stock options and other equity compensation plans. By using treasury shares to meet these obligations, the company avoids issuing new shares, which can be more cost-effective and administratively simpler.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Limit Dilution:</strong>
<ul>
<li>When a company issues new shares, for example, to raise capital or grant stock options, the ownership percentage of existing shareholders is diluted. By repurchasing shares, the company can mitigate or offset this dilution, helping to maintain or increase the earnings per share (EPS) and the ownership stake of existing shareholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Dual-class Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Dual-class shares refer to a structure where a company issues two classes of shares with different voting rights. Typically, one class (often Class A) has multiple votes per share, while the other class (often Class B) has fewer or no voting rights. This structure allows founders or insiders to maintain control over the company while raising capital through the sale of shares with limited voting rights to the public.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Founder&#8217;s Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Founder&#8217;s shares are shares typically issued to the founders of a company at its inception. These shares may have special rights or privileges, such as enhanced voting rights or preferential dividend treatment, to ensure that the founders retain control and benefit from the company&#8217;s success over the long term.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Basic Earnings Per Share (EPS)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li><strong>Definition:</strong> Basic EPS is a measure of a company&#8217;s profit or loss attributable to each outstanding common share.</li>



<li><strong>Calculation:</strong> It is computed using the weighted-average number of common shares outstanding during the period.</li>



<li><strong>Formula:</strong> Basic EPS = (Net Income &#8211; Preferred Dividends) / Weighted Average Number of Common Shares Outstanding</li>



<li><strong>Example:</strong> If a company has a net income of $1,000,000 and 1,000,000 common shares outstanding, the basic EPS would be $1.00 ($1,000,000 / 1,000,000 shares).</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Key Points:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Purpose:</strong> EPS figures provide insight into the profitability of each common share outstanding and are crucial metrics for investors assessing a company&#8217;s performance.</li>



<li><strong>Presentation:</strong> Companies are required to present both basic and diluted EPS on the face of their income statement to provide transparency regarding potential dilution from convertible securities.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Statements of Cash Flows II</title>
		<link>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:08:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=285</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inventories</title>
		<link>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:07:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=283</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Long-Term Assets</title>
		<link>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=281</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Topics in Long-Term Liabilities and Equity</title>
		<link>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/</link>
					<comments>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Analysis of Income Taxes</title>
		<link>/docs/analysis-of-income-taxes/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analysis-of-income-taxes/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=277</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analysis-of-income-taxes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Financial Reporting Quality</title>
		<link>/docs/financial-reporting-quality/</link>
					<comments>/docs/financial-reporting-quality/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=275</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/financial-reporting-quality/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Financial Analysis Techniques</title>
		<link>/docs/financial-analysis-techniques/</link>
					<comments>/docs/financial-analysis-techniques/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=273</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/financial-analysis-techniques/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Introduction to Financial Statement Modeling</title>
		<link>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-modeling/</link>
					<comments>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-modeling/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=271</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-modeling/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
