<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Financial Statement Analysis &#8211; Jamil Jahangir Sheikh</title>
	<atom:link href="/docs-category/financial-statement-analysis/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 15:55:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Blue-Business-Architecture-Design-Logo-Logos-150x150.png</url>
	<title>Financial Statement Analysis &#8211; Jamil Jahangir Sheikh</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Essential Financial Statement Analysis Terminology</title>
		<link>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/</link>
					<comments>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 16:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=319</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Learn about the key terminology that underpins the interpretation of balance sheets, income statements, and cash flow statements]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Financial statement analysis is a critical skill for investors, analysts, and stakeholders seeking to understand the financial health and performance of a company. To effectively analyze financial statements, one must be familiar with key terminology that underpins the interpretation of balance sheets, income statements, and cash flow statements. Below are some frequent terms and definitions to know:</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Accruals</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Accruals refer to revenues and expenses that have been recognized on the income statement before cash is exchanged. This concept is fundamental to accrual accounting, which matches revenues to the expenses incurred in generating them, rather than when payment is received or made.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Estimates</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Estimates involve the use of judgments and assumptions to determine values that are not directly observable. Examples include estimating the useful life of an asset for depreciation purposes or estimating the provision for bad debts.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Judgment</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Judgment refers to the exercise of discretion or discernment in making decisions, particularly in the context of financial reporting. It involves the application of professional skepticism and consideration of relevant facts and circumstances.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Management Policy Decisions</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Management policy decisions encompass the strategic choices made by a company&#8217;s management that impact financial reporting and operational outcomes. These decisions can include revenue recognition policies, inventory valuation methods, and capital expenditure policies.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Consistency</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Consistency in financial reporting refers to the application of accounting policies and methods consistently from one period to another. This allows for comparability of financial statements over time and enhances the reliability of financial analysis.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Carrying Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Carrying value, also known as book value, refers to the value at which an asset or liability is recognized on the balance sheet. It is usually the original cost less accumulated depreciation or amortization, impairment losses, or depletion.</li>



<li><strong>Historical Cost &#8211; Acc. Depreciation</strong></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recoverable Amount</strong></h4>



<p>Higher of the (fair value &#8211; costs to sell) &amp; (value in use)</p>



<p>Where,</p>



<ul>
<li>Fair value  &#8211; Amount obtainable in an arm&#8217;s length transaction</li>



<li>Value in use &#8211; Present value of future cash flows</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Impairment</strong></h4>



<p>This occurs when the<strong> carrying value </strong>of an asset <strong>exceed</strong>s its <strong>recoverable amount.</strong> The impairment loss is calculated as the difference between the carrying amount and the recoverable amount.</p>



<p>Impairment Loss = Carrying Value &#8211; Recoverable Amount</p>



<p><strong>Impact on Financial Statements:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Income Statement:</strong> Recognizes impairment loss as an <strong>expense</strong>, reducing net income for the period.</li>



<li><strong>Balance Sheet:</strong> <strong>Adjusts </strong>the carrying amount of the impaired asset to its recoverable amount, reducing <strong>total assets</strong>.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Flow Statement:</strong> This does not directly impact cash flows from operating activities but may affect <strong>investing activities</strong> if the <strong>impairment loss relates to non-current assets.</strong></li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Fair Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Fair value is the estimated price at which an asset or liability could be exchanged in an orderly transaction between knowledgeable and willing parties. Fair value measurements are used when assets and liabilities are reported at fair value on the balance sheet.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Realizable (Settlement) Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Realizable value, also known as settlement value, is the amount that would be received from selling an asset or settling a liability in an orderly transaction. It is crucial in assessing the liquidity and solvency of a company.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Accrual Accounting</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Accrual accounting is an accounting method that recognizes revenues and expenses when they are incurred, regardless of when cash transactions occur. It aims to provide a more accurate representation of a company&#8217;s financial position and performance.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Going Concern</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Going concern assumption assumes that a company will continue to operate in the foreseeable future. This assumption is fundamental in preparing financial statements under generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP).</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Recognition of Elements</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Recognition of elements involves including an item in the balance sheet or income statement if it meets the definition of an element (asset, liability, equity, income, or expense) and satisfies specific recognition criteria related to relevance and faithful representation.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Book Value</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Book value refers to the total amount of owner&#8217;s equity, also known as shareholders&#8217; equity, in a company. It represents the net assets of the company after deducting liabilities from assets.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Minority Interests (Non-controlling Interests)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Minority interests, or non-controlling interests, refer to the ownership stake in a subsidiary that is not owned by the parent company. These shareholders have a claim on the subsidiary&#8217;s profits and assets proportionate to their ownership percentage.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Allowance for Doubtful Accounts: (B/S item)</strong></h4>



<p>Accounts for expected losses from uncollectible receivables. Increases in this allowance correspondingly raise Bad debt expense is an accounting provision that represents the amount of expected losses from customers who are unable to pay their debts. It is recorded in the income statement as an expense.. When a debt is written off, only the allowance and accounts receivable are reduced, leaving bad debt expense unchanged.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Percentage of Uncollectable Receivable</strong></h4>



<p>% Uncollectable = Allowance for doubtful accounts/ Gross accounts receivable</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Bad Debt Expense (I/S Item)</strong></h4>



<p>When expected losses is added to allowance for doubtful accounts, the Bad debt expense is also increased by the same amount, it is an accounting provision that represents the amount of expected losses from customers who are unable to pay their debts. It is recorded in the income statement as an expense.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Concentration of Credit Risks</h4>



<p>Reported in notes &#8211; List of all customers that owe money in terms of % of AR they represent</p>



<p>Every time we add to Allowance for doubtful account, we add the same amount in Bad Debt Expense. So, in case of a write off, we only reduce the balance in the Allowance for doubtful account and in Accounts Receivable while Bad Dabt Expense remain untouched.</p>



<p>For Analysts, if you see a % change in the Allowance for doubtful accounts, find out why &#8211; Is there a change in Risk Management (more insurance), credit quality (better economy), or management change in estimates (could be to manipulate reported earnings (Overestimate Collectability, Underestimate Bad Debt Expense or Vice Versa).</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Revenue</h4>



<p>Amount charged for delivery of goods in the ordinary activities of a business. A.K.A. Sales / Turnover / Top line</p>



<p>Usually reported as Net Revenue ( After adjustments for Cash or volume discounts or other reductions in the revenue). Footnotes may mention of the items. </p>



<p>For comparative analysis,&nbsp; analyst may need to reference information disclosed elsewhere in companies’ annual reports</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Expenses</h4>



<p> Outflows &#8211; Depletion of assets &#8211; insurance of liabilities</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Net Income</h4>



<p><strong>Definition:</strong> Net income, also referred to as net earnings, profit or loss, profit of the year, or bottom line, is the total profit of a company after all expenses, taxes, and costs have been deducted from total revenue. It represents the company&#8217;s financial performance over a specific period.</p>



<p><strong>Components:</strong> Net income includes all gains and losses, even those not arising from ordinary business activities. For example, if a company sells surplus land that is not needed for operations, the transaction is reported as a gain or loss, calculated as the difference between the carrying value (the asset&#8217;s book value) and the selling price.</p>



<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> Details of such non-ordinary gains or losses are typically found in the financial statement disclosures, providing context and specifics about the nature and amount of these transactions.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Consolidation</h4>



<p><strong>Definition:</strong> Consolidation is the accounting process where a parent company combines the financial statements of its subsidiaries into one comprehensive set of financial statements. This occurs when the parent company has control over the subsidiary, typically evidenced by owning more than 50% of the subsidiary&#8217;s voting shares.</p>



<p><strong>Inclusion of Revenues and Expenses:</strong> When consolidating, the parent company includes all revenues and expenses of its subsidiaries in its consolidated financial statements, regardless of whether it owns less than 100% of the subsidiary. This ensures that the financial statements reflect the total economic activity and financial position of the combined entity.</p>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Noncontrolling Interest</strong></h5>



<p>Noncontrolling interest, also known as minority interest, represents the portion of the subsidiary&#8217;s income that is attributable to shareholders other than the parent company. This is the part of the subsidiary&#8217;s net income and equity that &#8220;belongs&#8221; to the minority shareholders and is reported separately in the consolidated financial statements.</p>



<p>We use the whole of a subsidiary in the consolidated statement. To balance the Asset and liability with Equity, we add the noncontrolling interests in the equity (Portion of subsidiary not that is not owned by the parent).</p>



<p><strong>Note For Analysts:</strong><br><strong>No Minority Interest:</strong> If there is <strong>goodwill</strong> on the balance sheet (Asset) but no minority interest in the equity, it means the parent company has fully acquired the subsidiary, owning 100% of its shares. Therefore, there are no minority shareholders.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Deferred Tax Assets</h4>



<p>Arise from temporary differences where the tax paid exceeds the tax expense reported on the income statement. It happens when you prepaid more than what is shown in the Income Statement due to Tax reporting and financial reporting differences. It may be amortized over several periods for accounting purposes</p>



<p>Represent future tax benefits due to overpayments or tax credits carried forward.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Accured Liability</h4>



<p>Accrued liabilities are expenses that have been reported on a company’s income statement but have not yet been paid.</p>



<p><strong>Example with Salary:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Suppose a company&#8217;s employees are paid on a bi-weekly basis, with the next payday falling after the end of the current accounting period.</li>



<li>At the end of the accounting period (e.g., December 31st), the company has accrued salaries owed to employees for the last few days of December.</li>



<li>Although the company hasn&#8217;t yet paid these salaries, it records them as an accrued liability on the balance sheet to reflect the amount owed.</li>



<li>This accrued liability ensures that the company&#8217;s financial statements accurately reflect its obligations and expenses incurred during the reporting period, even if cash payment occurs later.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Shares</h2>



<p>Shares (or stocks) typically refer to ownership units in a corporation. These shares can be categorized into different types based on the rights and privileges they confer to their holders. Here are the common types of shares:</p>



<p><li><strong>Capital Contributed by Owners:</strong><ul><li>The funds invested by shareholders through the purchase of shares, forming part of shareholders&#8217; equity.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Authorized Shares:</strong><ul><li>The maximum number of shares the company can issue, providing future financing flexibility.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Issued Shares:</strong><ul><li>The shares sold to investors, representing distributed ownership and capital raised.</li></ul></li><li><strong>Outstanding Shares:</strong><ul><li>The issued shares currently held by investors, used for financial calculations, excluding repurchased (treasury) shares.</li></ul></li></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Common Shares (Ordinary Shares)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Common shares are the most basic form of ownership in a corporation. Holders of common shares have voting rights in corporate decisions, such as the election of directors and major business decisions. They also have the potential to receive dividends, although these are not guaranteed and can fluctuate based on the company&#8217;s profitability and management decisions. In the event of liquidation, common shareholders are entitled to a portion of the company&#8217;s assets after creditors, bondholders, and preferred shareholders are paid.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Preferred Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Preferred shares are a class of ownership that typically does not carry voting rights but has a priority claim on dividends and assets over common shares. Preferred shareholders receive fixed dividends, which are often specified as a percentage of the share&#8217;s par value or as a fixed dollar amount. These dividends must be paid before any dividends can be distributed to common shareholders. In the event of liquidation, preferred shareholders have a priority claim on the company&#8217;s assets over common shareholders but are subordinate to creditors.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Redeemable Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Redeemable shares are shares that the issuer can buy back from shareholders at a predetermined price and time. These shares provide flexibility to the issuing company by allowing them to manage their capital structure effectively. The terms of redemption are typically outlined in the company&#8217;s articles of incorporation or shareholder agreements.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Treasury Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Treasury shares are shares that have been repurchased by the issuing company and are held in its treasury. These are shares that have been repurchased by the company but not canceled and can be reissued or retired depending on the company&#8217;s capital needs and strategic objectives.</li>



<li>Non-Voting / No Dividends.</li>



<li>Share repurchases reduce the company’s cash (an asset). Shareholders’ equity is reduced because there are fewer shares outstanding and treasury stock is an offset to owners’ equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Share Repurchases Impact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>When a company repurchases its own shares from the market, it uses cash to buy back these shares.</li>



<li>This reduces the company&#8217;s cash balance, which is categorized as an asset on the balance sheet.</li>



<li>Additionally, the number of shares outstanding decreases because the company holds these repurchased shares as treasury stock.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Effect on Shareholders&#8217; Equity:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Shareholders&#8217; equity decreases because there are fewer outstanding shares.</li>



<li>Treasury stock is subtracted from the total equity (owners&#8217; equity) on the balance sheet, acting as a contra-equity account.</li>



<li>The reduction in shareholders&#8217; equity reflects the decrease in the company&#8217;s ownership interest held by shareholders due to the share repurchase.</li>
</ul>



<h5 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Reasons for Repurchasing Treasury Shares:</strong></h5>



<ul>
<li><strong>Shares Undervalued:</strong>
<ul>
<li>When a company believes its shares are undervalued in the market, it may repurchase its shares to signal confidence in the company&#8217;s prospects and potentially boost the share price. This can enhance shareholder value as the market perceives the buyback as a positive signal about the company&#8217;s future.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>To Fulfill Options:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Companies often repurchase shares to have a reserve of stock available to fulfill employee stock options and other equity compensation plans. By using treasury shares to meet these obligations, the company avoids issuing new shares, which can be more cost-effective and administratively simpler.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Limit Dilution:</strong>
<ul>
<li>When a company issues new shares, for example, to raise capital or grant stock options, the ownership percentage of existing shareholders is diluted. By repurchasing shares, the company can mitigate or offset this dilution, helping to maintain or increase the earnings per share (EPS) and the ownership stake of existing shareholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Dual-class Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Dual-class shares refer to a structure where a company issues two classes of shares with different voting rights. Typically, one class (often Class A) has multiple votes per share, while the other class (often Class B) has fewer or no voting rights. This structure allows founders or insiders to maintain control over the company while raising capital through the sale of shares with limited voting rights to the public.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Founder&#8217;s Shares</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li>Founder&#8217;s shares are shares typically issued to the founders of a company at its inception. These shares may have special rights or privileges, such as enhanced voting rights or preferential dividend treatment, to ensure that the founders retain control and benefit from the company&#8217;s success over the long term.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Basic Earnings Per Share (EPS)</strong></h4>



<ul>
<li><strong>Definition:</strong> Basic EPS is a measure of a company&#8217;s profit or loss attributable to each outstanding common share.</li>



<li><strong>Calculation:</strong> It is computed using the weighted-average number of common shares outstanding during the period.</li>



<li><strong>Formula:</strong> Basic EPS = (Net Income &#8211; Preferred Dividends) / Weighted Average Number of Common Shares Outstanding</li>



<li><strong>Example:</strong> If a company has a net income of $1,000,000 and 1,000,000 common shares outstanding, the basic EPS would be $1.00 ($1,000,000 / 1,000,000 shares).</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Key Points:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>Purpose:</strong> EPS figures provide insight into the profitability of each common share outstanding and are crucial metrics for investors assessing a company&#8217;s performance.</li>



<li><strong>Presentation:</strong> Companies are required to present both basic and diluted EPS on the face of their income statement to provide transparency regarding potential dilution from convertible securities.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/essential-financial-statement-analysis-terminology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fundamental Concepts Related To Financial Statements</title>
		<link>/docs/fundamental-concepts-related-to-financial-statements/</link>
					<comments>/docs/fundamental-concepts-related-to-financial-statements/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 17:34:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=323</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Part 1: Financial Reporting 1. Objectives of Financial Statements 2. Enhancing Qualitative Characteristics of Financial Information 3. Constraints on Financial Statements 4. Assumptions of Financial Statements 5. Measurement of Financial Statement Elements 6. Qualitative Characteristics and Elements of Financial Statements 7. Role of Financial Reporting 8. Evaluation Tools in Financial Statements Part 2: Income Statement 1. Expenses on the Income Statement: Classification: 2. Expense Classification by Function: Examples: 3. Calculation of Gross Profit: Formula: 4. Common Size Income Statement: Definition: 5. Comprehensive Income Calculation: Components: 6. Other Comprehensive Income (OCI): Examples: 7. Items Classified as Other Comprehensive Income: Criteria: Part 3: Balance Sheet Equity is referred to as &#8220;Book Value&#8221;. &#8211; NOT market or intrinsic value. B/S has mixed model with respect to measurement. Some assets and liabilities are measured based on historical cost, sometimes with adjustments, whereas other assets and liabilities are measured based on a fair value, which represents its current value as of the balance sheet date. Some Company Valuation Factors not included in B/S: Current Liability: Payments due within one operating cycle of the business, even if they will be settled more than one year after the balance sheet date, are classified as current liabilities. Revenue Received in Advance: Resources Controlled by a Company: Equity Calculation: Difference Between Reported and Market Value of Shareholders&#8217; Equity: Classified Balance Sheet: Liquidity-Based Balance Sheet Presentation: Contra Asset Account: Current Liability Definition: Accrued Expenses (Accrued Liabilities): Debt Due Within One Year: Non-Controlling Interest in Consolidated Subsidiaries: Retained Earnings: Treasury Stock Transactions: Share Repurchases Impact: Part 4: Cash Flow Statement Converts the accrual-based income statement to a cash-based statement and provides a reconciliation between beginning an ending cash balances. Components: Noncash financing activities]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Part 1: Financial Reporting</h2>



<p><strong>1. Objectives of Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Financial statements serve to provide information about:
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial position</strong>: Assets, liabilities, and equity as of a specific date (Balance Sheet).</li>



<li><strong>Performance</strong>: Results of operations and net income for a period (Income Statement).</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>They also disclose information about changes in financial position and cash flows (Statement of Cash Flows).</li>



<li><strong>Objective</strong>: To aid users (investors, creditors, management, etc.) in making economic decisions.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>2. Enhancing Qualitative Characteristics of Financial Information</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Relevance</strong>: Information influences decisions by users.</li>



<li><strong>Faithful Representation</strong>: Information is complete, neutral, and free from error.</li>



<li><strong>Comparability</strong>: Information can be compared with similar information from other entities.</li>



<li><strong>Understandability</strong>: Information is understandable to users with reasonable knowledge of business and economic activities.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>3. Constraints on Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Cost vs. Benefit</strong>: The cost of providing information should not outweigh its benefits to users.</li>



<li><strong>Materiality</strong>: Information should be material enough to influence the decisions of users.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>4. Assumptions of Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Going Concern</strong>: Assumes the entity will continue operations in the foreseeable future.</li>



<li><strong>Accrual Basis</strong>: Transactions are recorded when they occur, not when cash is exchanged.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>5. Measurement of Financial Statement Elements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Historical Cost</strong>: Assets are recorded at the amount paid or fair value of consideration given at acquisition.</li>



<li><strong>Realizable Value</strong>: Assets are recorded at the amount that would be received in an orderly disposal.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>6. Qualitative Characteristics and Elements of Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Performance Measurement</strong>: Primarily evaluated through the income statement, which shows revenues and expenses over a period.</li>



<li><strong>Financial Position</strong>: Assessed through the balance sheet, detailing assets, liabilities, and equity at a specific date.</li>



<li><strong>Shareholder’s Residual Claim</strong>: Reflects owners&#8217; equity, the residual interest in assets after deducting liabilities, presented on the balance sheet.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>7. Role of Financial Reporting</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Purpose</strong>: Provide information about the financial position, performance, and changes in financial position of an entity.</li>



<li><strong>Users</strong>: Aid users in making economic decisions based on the financial information presented.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>8. Evaluation Tools in Financial Statements</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Income Statement</strong>: Used to assess profitability and financial results from business activities over a period.</li>



<li><strong>Balance Sheet</strong>: Evaluates the financial position by showing assets, liabilities, and equity at a specific date.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Flow Statement</strong>: Analyzes the sources and uses of cash flows during a period.</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Part 2: Income Statement</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Expenses on the Income Statement:</h3>



<p><strong>Classification:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Expenses on the income statement can be grouped by either nature or function.</li>



<li><strong>Nature:</strong> Classifies expenses based on what they are (e.g., salaries, rent, depreciation).</li>



<li><strong>Function:</strong> Classifies expenses based on their purpose or role in the operation (e.g., cost of goods sold, selling expenses, administrative expenses).</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Expense Classification by Function:</h3>



<p><strong>Examples:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Cost of Goods Sold (COGS):</strong> Represents the direct costs incurred in producing goods sold by the company.</li>



<li><strong>Other Examples:</strong> Manufacturing costs, production overheads, and costs associated with sales and marketing.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. Calculation of Gross Profit:</h3>



<p><strong>Formula:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Gross Profit = Revenue &#8211; Cost of Goods Sold (COGS)</strong></li>



<li>Example Calculation:
<ul>
<li>Revenue: $4,000,000</li>



<li>COGS: $3,000,000</li>



<li>Gross Profit = $4,000,000 &#8211; $3,000,000 = $1,000,000</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. Common Size Income Statement:</h3>



<p><strong>Definition:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>A common size income statement presents each line item as a percentage of revenue.</li>



<li>Facilitates comparison across time periods (time-series analysis) and across companies (cross-sectional analysis).</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. Comprehensive Income Calculation:</h3>



<p><strong>Components:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Net Income:</strong> The profit earned during the period from primary business activities.</li>



<li><strong>Other Comprehensive Income (OCI):</strong> Includes items that affect shareholders&#8217; equity but are not part of net income.</li>



<li><strong>Example Calculation:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Net Income: $15 million</li>



<li>OCI Components: Unrealized gain on available-for-sale securities ($5 million), Unrealized loss on derivatives accounted for as hedges (-$3 million), Foreign currency translation gain on consolidation ($2 million)</li>



<li>Comprehensive Income = Net Income + OCI</li>



<li>Comprehensive Income = $15 million + $4 million = $19 million</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">6. Other Comprehensive Income (OCI):</h3>



<p><strong>Examples:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Foreign Currency Translation Adjustment:</strong> Reflects gains or losses from translating financial statements of foreign subsidiaries.</li>



<li><strong>Unrealized Gain on Available-for-Sale Securities:</strong> Unrealized gains or losses on investments classified as available-for-sale.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">7. Items Classified as Other Comprehensive Income:</h3>



<p><strong>Criteria:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Items that affect shareholders&#8217; equity but are not included in net income.</li>



<li>Examples: Foreign currency translation adjustments, unrealized gains or losses on available-for-sale securities.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Part 3: Balance Sheet</h3>



<p>Equity is referred to as &#8220;Book Value&#8221;. &#8211; NOT market or intrinsic value.</p>



<p>B/S has mixed model with respect to measurement. Some assets and liabilities are measured based on historical cost, sometimes with adjustments, whereas other assets and liabilities are measured based on a fair value, which represents its current value as of the balance sheet date.</p>



<ul>
<li>Assets or liabilities on the balance sheet are valued at their fair market value as of the reporting date.</li>



<li>However, these values can fluctuate post-reporting period due to changing economic conditions or market dynamics.</li>



<li>Thus, while the balance sheet provides a snapshot of a company&#8217;s financial position at a specific moment, the actual value of these items may change after the reporting date.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Some Company Valuation Factors not included in B/S:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Future cash flows projected by the company.</li>



<li>Current market conditions impacting demand and pricing.</li>



<li>However, crucial aspects affecting future cash flow generation, like reputation and management expertise, are not quantified in the balance sheet.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Current Liability: </strong>Payments due within one <strong>operating cycle</strong> of the business, even if they will be settled more than one year after the balance sheet date, are classified as current liabilities.</p>



<p><strong>Revenue Received in Advance:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>When a company receives money from customers for products to be delivered in the future &#8211; Recorded as both an asset and a liability. Ex. Cash as asset and Unearned revenue as the liability. As the product is delivered, revenue will be recognized and the liability will be reduced.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Resources Controlled by a Company:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Assets are resources controlled by a company.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Equity Calculation:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Equity equals Assets minus Liabilities.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Difference Between Reported and Market Value of Shareholders&#8217; Equity:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Market value differs due to factors not reflected in the balance sheet, such as reputation and management skills.</li>



<li>The balance sheet measures some assets and liabilities based on historical cost and measures others based on current value. Whereas, Market value of shareholders’ equity is updated continuously.</li>



<li>Shareholders’ equity reported on the balance sheet is updated for reporting purposes and represents the value that was current at the end of the reporting period. not the current one.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Classified Balance Sheet:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Distinguishes between current and non-current items.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Liquidity-Based Balance Sheet Presentation:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Used by banks to list assets and liabilities by liquidity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Contra Asset Account:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Offsets the balance of a related asset account, such as allowance for doubtful accounts.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Current Liability Definition:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Obligations due within one year or the operating cycle. Ex. payment due at least one year after the balance sheet date but still within a normal operating cycle.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Accrued Expenses (Accrued Liabilities):</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Expenses recognized on the income statement but not yet paid.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Debt Due Within One Year:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Classified as a current liability.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Non-Controlling Interest in Consolidated Subsidiaries:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Shown separately as part of shareholders&#8217; equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Retained Earnings:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Component of shareholders’ equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Treasury Stock Transactions:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Reduces both assets and shareholders’ equity.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Share Repurchases Impact:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>When a company repurchases its own shares from the market, it uses cash to buy back these shares.</li>



<li>This <strong>reduces</strong> the company&#8217;s <strong>cash</strong> balance, which is categorized as an <strong>asset </strong>on the <strong>balance sheet.</strong></li>



<li>Additionally, the <strong>number of shares outstanding</strong> <strong>decreases</strong> because the company holds these repurchased shares as treasury stock.</li>



<li>Treasury stock represents shares that the company buys back and holds in its treasury, effectively reducing the total number of shares available to the public.</li>



<li><strong>Effect on Shareholders&#8217; Equity:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Shareholders&#8217; equity<strong> decreases </strong>because there are <strong>fewer outstanding shares.</strong></li>



<li><strong>Treasury stock</strong> is <strong>subtracted </strong>from the total equity (owners&#8217; equity) on the balance sheet, acting as a contra-equity account.</li>



<li>The reduction in shareholders&#8217; equity reflects the decrease in the<strong> company&#8217;s ownership interest <em>held by shareholders</em></strong> due to the share repurchase.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Part 4: Cash Flow Statement</h2>



<p>Converts the accrual-based income statement to a cash-based statement and provides a reconciliation between beginning an ending cash balances.</p>



<p>Components:</p>



<ol>
<li>Operating Activities 
<ul>
<li>Inflows
<ul>
<li>Cash Sales &#8211; Revenue generated from sales where payment is received immediately in cash. To generate revenue, companies undertake such activities as manufacturing inventory, purchasing inventory from suppliers, and paying employees. If we are in the business of trading securities &#8211; Sales of dealing securities or trading securities can be considered cash inflow, and if we are in a different business, that would be considered an investing activity.</li>



<li>Decreases in Assets &#8211; a collection of accounts receivable</li>



<li>Increases in liabilities &#8211; Increases in the bank line of credit means we have more.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Investing activities
<ul>
<li>purchasing and selling
<ul>
<li>Long term assets &#8211; PPE, Factory/Infrastructure (LT), Intangible assets, other LTA. Investment in both<strong> short</strong>-term (cash equivalents) And <strong>long-</strong>term assets is equity and debt (bonds and loans) issued by other companies.</li>



<li>non-trading securities</li>



<li>Almost any non current assets.</li>



<li>When doing calculations for <strong>NET CASH FLOW </strong>&#8211; you might see an item as &#8220;<strong>Loss on sale</strong>&#8220;. That would be a loss from selling the item at an amount less than the book value, and that is a NON-CASH item. Our only concern should be the <strong><em>Purchase of the Item</em></strong> &amp; <strong><em>Proceeds from the sale. </em></strong>The difference between the two would be our <strong>NET CASH FLOW</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Financing Activities
<ul>
<li>obtaining or repaying capital,</li>



<li>Sources
<ul>
<li>Shareholders &#8211; Equity</li>



<li>Creditors &#8211; Long term debt</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Cash Inflows:</strong> Include proceeds from issuing stock (common or preferred) or bonds, and cash received from borrowing.</li>



<li><strong>Cash Outflows:</strong> Include payments for repurchasing stock (e.g., treasury stock), and for repaying bonds and other borrowings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<p>Noncash financing activities</p>



<ul>
<li>No cash, no cash flow reporting. </li>



<li>Examples: 
<ul>
<li>Barter, </li>



<li>Stock Dividends ( a way to distribute earnings or capitalize retained earnings while conserving cash, basically giving additional shares instead of cash ), </li>



<li>conversion of convertible securities.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/fundamental-concepts-related-to-financial-statements/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Introduction to Financial Statement Analysis</title>
		<link>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-analysis/</link>
					<comments>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-analysis/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:03:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=263</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS vs US GAAP) Topic U.S. GAAP IFRS Similarities Example Purpose of Framework The FASB framework is lower in the hierarchy and isn&#8217;t prioritized if no standard exists. Management must follow the IASB framework if no standard or interpretation is available. Both assist in developing and understanding standards. In the U.S., if a specific standard isn&#8217;t available, management might not refer to the FASB framework, while in Europe, management must use the IASB framework for guidance. Objectives of Financial Statements Provides different objectives for business and non-business entities. Gives one objective for all business entities. Both aim to provide relevant information to a wide range of users. Both frameworks aim to inform stakeholders like investors and creditors, despite having different objectives for business and non-business entities under U.S. GAAP. Underlying Assumptions Recognizes accrual and going concern but doesn&#8217;t emphasize them much. Emphasizes accrual and going concern bases. Both use accrual and going concern assumptions. An IFRS-compliant company&#8217;s financial statements assume ongoing operations indefinitely, similar to the concept under U.S. GAAP but with more emphasis. Qualitative Characteristics Uses understandability, relevance, reliability, and comparability with a hierarchy. Uses the same characteristics without a hierarchy. Both frameworks use the same qualitative characteristics. While IFRS treats all characteristics equally, U.S. GAAP prioritizes relevance and reliability over comparability and understandability. Approach Historically rules-based, moving towards an object-oriented approach. Principles-based approach. &#8211; IFRS relies on broad principles for financial reporting, whereas U.S. GAAP has detailed rules but is moving towards a more principle-based approach. Performance Elements Elements include revenues, expenses, gains, losses, and comprehensive income. Elements are revenues and expenses. &#8211; Under IFRS, performance is measured by revenues and expenses, while U.S. GAAP also includes gains, losses, and comprehensive income. Financial Position Elements Assets are future economic benefits; &#8220;probable&#8221; is used in definitions. Assets are future economic resources expected to provide benefits; &#8220;probable&#8221; is part of the criteria. Both define assets and liabilities in terms of future benefits and obligations. Both frameworks define assets as future economic benefits, but IFRS explicitly uses &#8220;probable&#8221; in its criteria for recognizing assets and liabilities. Recognition of Elements Does not use &#8220;probable&#8221; for recognition; uses &#8220;relevance&#8221; as a criterion. Requires &#8220;probable&#8221; future economic benefits for recognition. &#8211; IFRS requires that an asset be recognized if it is probable that future benefits will flow to the entity, unlike U.S. GAAP which uses relevance without explicitly stating &#8220;probable&#8221;. Measurement of Elements Generally prohibits revaluation, except for certain categories discussed later. Revaluation is usually permitted. Both use historical cost, current cost, and other measurement attributes. IFRS allows revaluation of assets like property, whereas U.S. GAAP typically does not, except in certain circumstances discussed in later sections.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS vs US GAAP)</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><thead><tr><th><strong>Topic</strong></th><th><strong>U.S. GAAP</strong></th><th><strong>IFRS</strong></th><th><strong>Similarities</strong></th><th><strong>Example</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Purpose of Framework</strong></td><td>The FASB framework is lower in the hierarchy and isn&#8217;t prioritized if no standard exists.</td><td>Management must follow the IASB framework if no standard or interpretation is available.</td><td>Both assist in developing and understanding standards.</td><td>In the U.S., if a specific standard isn&#8217;t available, management might not refer to the FASB framework, while in Europe, management must use the IASB framework for guidance.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Objectives of Financial Statements</strong></td><td>Provides different objectives for business and non-business entities.</td><td>Gives one objective for all business entities.</td><td>Both aim to provide relevant information to a wide range of users.</td><td>Both frameworks aim to inform stakeholders like investors and creditors, despite having different objectives for business and non-business entities under U.S. GAAP.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Underlying Assumptions</strong></td><td>Recognizes accrual and going concern but doesn&#8217;t emphasize them much.</td><td>Emphasizes accrual and going concern bases.</td><td>Both use accrual and going concern assumptions.</td><td>An IFRS-compliant company&#8217;s financial statements assume ongoing operations indefinitely, similar to the concept under U.S. GAAP but with more emphasis.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Qualitative Characteristics</strong></td><td>Uses understandability, relevance, reliability, and comparability with a hierarchy.</td><td>Uses the same characteristics without a hierarchy.</td><td>Both frameworks use the same qualitative characteristics.</td><td>While IFRS treats all characteristics equally, U.S. GAAP prioritizes relevance and reliability over comparability and understandability.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Approach</strong></td><td>Historically rules-based, moving towards an object-oriented approach.</td><td>Principles-based approach.</td><td>&#8211;</td><td>IFRS relies on broad principles for financial reporting, whereas U.S. GAAP has detailed rules but is moving towards a more principle-based approach.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Performance Elements</strong></td><td>Elements include revenues, expenses, gains, losses, and comprehensive income.</td><td>Elements are revenues and expenses.</td><td>&#8211;</td><td>Under IFRS, performance is measured by revenues and expenses, while U.S. GAAP also includes gains, losses, and comprehensive income.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Financial Position Elements</strong></td><td>Assets are future economic benefits; &#8220;probable&#8221; is used in definitions.</td><td>Assets are future economic resources expected to provide benefits; &#8220;probable&#8221; is part of the criteria.</td><td>Both define assets and liabilities in terms of future benefits and obligations.</td><td>Both frameworks define assets as future economic benefits, but IFRS explicitly uses &#8220;probable&#8221; in its criteria for recognizing assets and liabilities.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Recognition of Elements</strong></td><td>Does not use &#8220;probable&#8221; for recognition; uses &#8220;relevance&#8221; as a criterion.</td><td>Requires &#8220;probable&#8221; future economic benefits for recognition.</td><td>&#8211;</td><td>IFRS requires that an asset be recognized if it is probable that future benefits will flow to the entity, unlike U.S. GAAP which uses relevance without explicitly stating &#8220;probable&#8221;.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Measurement of Elements</strong></td><td>Generally prohibits revaluation, except for certain categories discussed later.</td><td>Revaluation is usually permitted.</td><td>Both use historical cost, current cost, and other measurement attributes.</td><td>IFRS allows revaluation of assets like property, whereas U.S. GAAP typically does not, except in certain circumstances discussed in later sections.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/introduction-to-financial-statement-analysis/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Income Statements</title>
		<link>/docs/analyzing-income-statements/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analyzing-income-statements/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:04:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=265</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analyzing-income-statements/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Balance Sheets</title>
		<link>/docs/analyzing-balance-sheets/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analyzing-balance-sheets/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=267</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analyzing-balance-sheets/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Statements of Cash Flows I</title>
		<link>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-i/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-i/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-i/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Statements of Cash Flows II</title>
		<link>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:08:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=285</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analyzing-statements-of-cash-flows-ii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inventories</title>
		<link>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:07:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=283</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analysis-of-inventories/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Long-Term Assets</title>
		<link>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/</link>
					<comments>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=281</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/analysis-of-long-term-assets/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Topics in Long-Term Liabilities and Equity</title>
		<link>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/</link>
					<comments>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jamil]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:06:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/?post_type=docs#038;p=279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/docs/topics-in-long-term-liabilities-and-equity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
